[Music]
robert thank you very much for joining
me
my pleasure thanks for having me yeah
i've been a i followed your work for a
long time
and i've been very impressed by your
books you're the author of two books mad
in america an anatomy of an epidemic
you've been investigating the the
dangers of long-term use of psychiatric
drugs for decades
and i think you're also nominated for a
pulitzer prize at one point for you for
your work
i was actually a finalist one or three
great so you were fine it's pretty easy
to get nominated to be honest with you
yeah so i've also
looked into this quite a bit myself for
a potential documentary for the bbc a
few years ago
um and looked at your work um would you
like to just start off by summarizing
your work
um for people who maybe aren't familiar
with it it's a very big picture
yeah no i think the big picture is this
you know starting in 1980 which is when
the third edition of the diagnostic and
statistical manual was
published by the american psychiatric
association starting in the united
states but then it expanded
we got a narrative that was told to the
public and our societies organized
themselves around the narrative which we
were told was scientific and the
narrative is quite simple
is that they had this they were
discovering that these are brain
diseases these are brain illnesses
depression
anxiety psychosis
and most important that it seemed that
they were due to chemical imbalances in
the brain
and that the drugs we had fix those
chemical imbalances like insulin for
diabetes that's the story we were sold
it's a story of great scientific
progress when you think about it right
think about how complex the brain is the
human brain
and they had identified the very
molecule that causes madness depression
anxiety and they could fix it if that's
so i'd say that's the greatest discovery
in
maybe scientific history given the
complexity of the brain
and then we heard you know then we got
stories about these new drugs that were
so much better than the first generation
psychiatric drugs prozac of course was
the first but we got new antipsychotics
etc
and with that narrative our use of
reversal diagnoses expanded but our use
of psychiatric drugs just expanded first
in the united states
and by the way to people of all ages i
mean we started
medicating our kids to our elderly
people and initially there was some
resistance in europe to medicating the
kids and
but gradually this story took hold
really around the world
now my work i think in
writ large is this is to say is it true
it does and by the way not from the
critics does their own
scientific literature um
support that story so and what you find
is that the chemical imbalance
theory was always a hypothesis
so for example we've heard that
depression is due to um
too little serotonin and it drugs up
serotonin okay
well you can go back and you can see
that hypothesis really arises in the
1960s
and you can see by 1984 the nimh is
saying
listen we're just not finding that
people who are depressed
have low serotonin and then in 1998 the
american psychiatric association's own
textbook says you know the chemical
imbalance theory was
a pretty um naive
theory in the first place it wasn't it
wasn't you know there was really no
reason
that the cause of a problem should be
the opposite of the drug's mechanism of
action
and they said it's gone it didn't we
didn't confirm it
and you can go kenneth candler in 2004
he was a world leader in investigating
says hey we've hunted for these chemical
imbalances we haven't found them
that's what's in the scientific
literature but that's not what was being
told to the public
and that includes by the american
psychiatric association now that's the
first part you can and so you see this
this narrative of progress starts to
fall apart
so the irony the real irony of the whole
chemical imbalance story is this
in scientific terms a
the whole theory arose because of an
understanding of how the drugs acted on
the brain
how they perturbed normal functioning
okay
and what they found is that before
people went on the drugs they didn't
have any characteristic chemical
imbalance
but they found that once you go on these
drugs they induce
a physiological change opposite of the
drug's mechanism of an action
that is the very thing that was
hypothesized to cause say psychosis
or depression in the first place
that's what the science showed and what
is so amazing is you see this worry
going
all the way back to the 70s and the
worry that antidepressants
actually were depressogenic agents uh
over the long term that you can trace
that back to the 80s but especially then
in the 90s
so that's a very long-winded answer
david to say that
in simple terms we as a society have
organized ourselves
around this narrative of scientific
progress
now uh you know i'm not a scientist
right
i didn't do the research but you can go
and look at that research and you find
that the
scientific story
is quite different okay and
unfortunately what you find over the
long term again and again is
that we are worsening
the natural course of these disorders
over the long term in the aggregate
so we're talking now specifically
because of the news about jordan
peterson
and he just put out a video yesterday
um talking about his history with
benzodiazepines
and warning people not to take them for
more than two weeks that this is
that he's very worried about those drugs
can you talk specifically about
benzodiazepines in this context what
how do they work and how does the brain
kind of compensate
why is it so dangerous to be taking them
for for a length of time
yeah the benzel story is really amazing
because
doctors have known these drugs for a
long time shouldn't be taken long
two or three weeks so that's not even
new knowledge
that became like the official
recommendation in 1980
uh here's here's the thing so when we
talk about serotonin and dopamine
they're they're basically excitatory
neurons excitatory um
neurotransmitters what does that mean
you have a presynaptic neuron right
and it releases and let's say it's a
dopaminergic neuron it releases that
dopamine
it binds with receptors on the so this
is the presynaptic neuron the
postsynaptic neuron
and since it's an excitatory neuron it
causes this neuron to fire
okay and that's how messages are passed
along
but the brain at the same think of a car
has an accelerator
it also has a break right and and that's
how you sort of maintain
brain function because you have
molecules that can excite things so they
get molecules that can acquire things
well the molecule that
quiets things the main molecules called
gaba and
so what happens is it with a with a gaba
neurotransmitter it it it inhibits the
firing of the second neuron it makes it
less likely to fire so it's a quieting
thing
so what a benzodiazepine does is it
amps up the gaba system it's like
slamming the brake on on
on neuronal activity so that's why you
you know that's why um you know your
emotions
you know you feel relaxed or you don't
care your anxiety goes
it's because the the benzo when you
first take it
is quieting your your your
your brain in essence and your whole
system
and this is why also if you don't take
too many pencils you'll stop breathing
right
um so what what is again so what happens
so this is your braking system right so
you go into benzo
and benzo is amplifying gaba
it it gets into the gaba receptors so it
acts as a gaba substitute
so your brain goes ah i'm doing too much
inhibit inhibition there's too much
inhibitory of of my regular functioning
so it starts
reducing its uh
gaba receptors and its own production of
gaba
so think about this it's the normal
break
right now what you do is with the drug
you
press harder on that break all right
it's like you're putting your foot down
but the brain's own braking mechanism
then
starts becoming less effective okay
so now go off your benzo
right what do you got you've lost your
braking system
or it's become diminished so that's why
for example you hear people coming off
how i've got these weird skin
sensations and all these things is
because your neurons are firing
like crazy out of control because you
have
you have at the very least lessened
that natural braking system now the
other thing that people don't realize so
i take a benzo for four weeks now i can
either go off
i can keep on many people keep on well
the best
the best long-term studies we have show
that over the long term even if you stay
on your
uh benzo you're more likely to become
anxious okay it's like the drug because
of this whole change in your brain
system it starts losing
the speculums speculation so even if you
stay on you'll see
if you do comparison between a group
that never took it
and one that stayed on you'll see that
the group continually on will have more
anxiety more panic episodes
more likely to be start you know
agoraphobia
you know all these things that we
associate with it so
long long to summarize all this
there's some evidence you can use these
drugs for two weeks
with some effectiveness and particularly
in difficult times
but beyond that you're getting into a
place where it's quite clear
that you're setting yourself up for
difficult times
uh trouble getting off and if you stay
on um
more emotional problems and by the way
cognitive uh
impairments too yeah i remember reading
your
your work and it just seems so clear
that because the brain
is a an adaptive system
it's adapting to this perturbations that
you're having from the
from not just benzos but all all
psychiatric drugs
and then especially if you're taking it
for anxiety and your brain is then
effectively kind of
um ramping up the the receptors for
anxiety when you're coming off them
you are then super super sensitized for
the very thing that you were trying to
dull down in the first place one thing
i'd like to
ask you about because i've seen jordan
peterson and his daughter talk about
that he was prescribed it for a food
allergy
and then increasingly over over time
developed what he described as a very
unusual
reaction to to benzos where they were
actually making him more anxious rather
than less
and from what i understand from your
work at least that's not actually that
unusual to
that you once over time you start to
actually become
become more and more sensitized to the
very thing that you're trying to block
what would you how would you reflect on
that no i think you just got it right
no i i mean this is part of the tragedy
of this whole thing
that you come there for some short
relief
and short-term relief but you're setting
yourself up if you stay on these very
long for
for a difficult process either the
difficult thing of coming off
or just as you said because the brain
has changed
more everyday anxiety and
there there is a a mechanism that
explains it and the mechanism that
you're is
is you're taking away the brain's own
braking system
physiologically and i don't know if we
understand
so the brain's trying to maintain a
homeostatic equilibrium right it's
trying to put its
break it so you go on a benzo as to your
braking system
it's like you're pressing down harder on
the braking system and so
the braking system itself sort of dims
its own
force and you think that's a that's an
equilibrium so maybe if i just stay on
the drug this will be a new way for the
brain to
act but it seems like the brain's
that compensatory system actually
becomes a bit dysfunctional as much as
anything
so it's not that you really reach a new
equilibrium
but as opposed to a sort of
you know new eq a new way of you know
like one foot on the brake one for an
accelerator
and it seems like it leads over time to
sort of a dysfunctionality
so you see like often more psychotic
symptoms
in psychotic patients on antipsychotics
long term
and that's thought because that
this the brain is becoming so super
sensitive to dopamine
that it's it's now in this abnormal
state with depression the idea is it
drives your brain into this
look actually a very sort of
dysfunctional serotonergic state
so benzo if you continually take it it
seems like it's
probably driving your gaba system which
is your braking system
into a dysfunctional state i mean in
other words
there's this immediate effort for the
brain to maintain a homeostatic
equilibrium
but it seems that it's such a stressor
on the brain
it becomes to become it tends to become
less functional over time
and i i think this metaphor can maybe
illuminate this in a little way so you
get in your car okay
so so go ahead and get in your car foot
put
start to drive put one foot on the
accelerator okay
and now as you start driving put your
other foot on the brake and this is how
you decide to go down the road okay
you're using both systems and now drive
your car like that for 10 years
is it going to be it's going to be very
effective functional
you know systems wear out is what i'm
trying to say
if that makes sense i i think that's a
metaphor
to explain how over time
you're getting these this these signs of
dysfunction
yeah you've already kind of hinted at it
but i'd like to broaden this out a
little bit
um why i think this is such a vitally
important conversation
is sort of the wider issue of
biatrogenic
damage which is the word that means
damage caused by medical interventions
and i've heard a few people contact of
mine talk about the
iatrogenic plague what i understand is
that when people often go on to a
psychiatric drug
and they then have these side effects
it's then often attributed to
the condition that they originally
presented with
but they are often then in this kind of
system of a different cocktail of drugs
moving from one to the other and they
all have quite they can all
collectively have quite damaging effects
can you talk about that sort of catch-22
situation that people find themselves in
and how that plays out just in a sort of
a bigger picture well in a way i think
you've summarized it quite good
it's quite well um that's exactly right
so what happens is
uh so you you start down this path okay
and often
you get down this path with just a mild
problem right
you come in you have a mild problem
you're looking for maybe you've got
divorced or you
lost a job or something has happened
okay
maybe you're not sleeping and so you
start down this path where
your brain is going to be changed by a
drug
and as we were discussing earlier very
often it
poops out the positive effect that sort
of control of the symptoms
poops out over time right so what
happens when it poops out
do you blame and and maybe new symptoms
are coming up
right oh i wasn't depressed before now
i'm depressed
i wasn't anxious before now i'm anxious
the proper medical thing would be to say
ah
the drug has stopped working and maybe
it's indeed inducing those problems
that's the iatrogenic damage
but people who prescribe drugs don't
want to admit that their drugs are doing
harm
they only want to see them through a
prism of doing help
even though we all know that drugs can
do harm that's not how the prescriber
or the uh you know the medical
profession of psychiatry wants to see
its drugs so what they do
is as they start saying that um
[Music]
people are treatment resistant or you
know it's the illness
that is is what you're seeing now is the
illness return
and once that happens what happens you
go on a second drug you go on the third
drug you go on a fourth drug
now if you start on one and end up on
four drugs
uh that's a sign of medical failure
right
i mean no one says polar pharmacy is
good
and what it means is you've you've
started having new symptoms and so
you're moving to new
symptoms new dysfunction and what you
get on four or five drugs boy i mean
it's hard to function well on four or
five drugs
and you can't imagine the number of
stories that i mean you can't but
there's so many stories like
i went on just the other night i met i i
was in i was
talking to someone who in their
sophomore year of college
they broke up with a girlfriend and
as a result failed chemistry so
he was put on the benzo he was anxious
32 years later he was trying to taper
from the bento
he wasn't working he'd been on
any number of drugs it all started when
he broke up with his girlfriend like
when he's 20 years old
but that's part of the um
narrative that really is a uh
misleads the public with that when
people when you see people deteriorate
on these medications long term
it's blamed to the disease even though
there's no evidence that this is the
natural course of things
and in that way they preserve they
preserve the image of the drugs as as
you know as helpful and all the problems
get assigned to the disease
but there's no evidence for that and and
and david one thing i think that's
really important here
what's the natural course of these
problems because
in order to assess whether a drug is
doing harm
over the long term okay or providing a
benefit
you have to know the natural course what
is the natural capacity to recover
so what is the long-term course your
drug in order to be beneficial
has to beat that natural recovery rate
so let's say
the natural recovery rate from
depression is 80 which by the way is
what it used to be called and and that
two years later let's say
80 are not depressed okay for your drug
to be
beneficial over two years you have to
have a recovery rate of like 85
and but you don't see that you'll see
like well actually the recovery rate on
antidepressants is terrible
but in the best long in a in a couple
long-term studies we had in the united
states you know what
stay well rate was at the end of one
year
in real clinical settings and one it was
three percent
and and the other was about uh i think
it was about six percent
and as the the researchers said these
are astonishingly
low um you know stay well rates and when
they did those studies they said
these are real world studies we're not
going to be doing these pharma-funded
studies where you're
you're trying to pick a select group of
people
now at the same time but anyway
so what are you doing you're taking the
natural recovery rate and you're
lowering it
anyway that's the way to think about
this it's not that everybody does poorly
on their drugs but what are you doing to
outcomes in the aggregate and the
optimistic part of this whole story is
if we go back
it's recovery rates in the natural world
from an episode of depression
an episode of anxiety anxiety in
particular was seen as
transient um or even psychosis
we're so often seen as episodic you'll
get through it
and when we talk about depression as
episode we're talking about people got
hospitalized for depression we're not
talking about this walking around
depression
hospitalized depression clinical
depression and
even hospitalized patients about 80
percent would be well within one year
and they they did a modern study on this
and they said what's the
recovery rate for depression in modern
times okay they finally did this
in the absence of drugs you know what
the recovery weight was at the end of
one year 85
so in the medicated arm it was like 10
in the in the in the unmedicated arm it
was like 85
and if you read that story the
researchers go wow really be hard for a
drug
to beat this recovery yeah i just
wonder if you could summarize
quite briefly just what you think are
the most damning statistics
or the most kind of compelling evidence
for the damage that's being done
of of the of these drugs well in anatomy
of an epidemic what i did is i just
looked at as a marker of disability okay
so i looked at the number of people who
were ending up on government disability
due to mental illness okay
now that's the extreme end right they
can no longer work
well in 1987 we had about 1.25 million
adults
on disability due to mental illness okay
then we get this that's when prozac
comes to market we get this explosion in
the use of drugs
and now today it's around five million
uh
adults on disability united states and
by the way it's gone up in every country
i can find
that embrace this story and the use of
antidepressants and all
uh like in the uk um
nor you know in any scandinavian
countries australia new zealand you see
it over and over again
the second thing is like what's
happening to the kids
so you see with this increasing use of
psychiatric drugs the mental health of
kids is deteriorating
in the united states something like well
first of all just on disability
in 1987 when prozac came to market we
had 16 000 kids
whose families or guardians received a
payment because the kid was dis
the child was disabled by mental illness
it's something like seven or eight
hundred thousand now
so you know that's like uh what is that
a 40 time increase 40 fold increase
and if you look at kids who end up
psychiatrized
and sort of um you know
if they end up on disability two-thirds
go on to uh
adult disability when they turn age 18.
but the most amazing thing is something
like
50 of american students now
seek mental health during their four
years of college
so i see this disability like the canary
in the cold ma
coal mine in other words
that's that's a marker of harm done
but all the markers suicide's gone up
like 20 years in a row in the united
states
um the burden of depression globally has
increased dramatically and i'm not
saying it's only due to the drugs
but all the markers of psychiatric
distress and developed societies have
basically gone
up in the last uh 30 years
so that's on just um if we just see this
as a story of a medical failure okay if
we just look at this through a medical
lens
the larger failure is this is also a
story of philosophy
because think about what the chemical
imbalance story is telling you
it's sort of telling you that these
chemicals in your brain control you
right
that you're sort of the the robot to
these master chemicals
and it takes away a sense of
of responsibility for oneself right
because it's not your responsibility
that you're unhappy
or whatever um
whereas if you have a different
philosophy and the philosophy
is listen to suffer is to be human
we're gonna be anxious we're gonna be
depressed sometimes
and even to go a bit mad is not all that
unusual especially if you stop sleeping
and stuff
but if we have like an older style of
that first of all we have a
you know if we look at as a philosophy
you see in novels and shakespeare and
all
we understand that humans suffer we also
understand that the human mind is not a
pleasant place sometimes
it's a difficult place
that becomes your philosophy of
understanding what it means to be human
it ain't easy growing up ain't easy so
when you suffer you're depressed you're
grieving
okay and you're a bit crazy that's what
humans
are at the same time we understand in
that philosophy we understand we're
responsive to our environment that maybe
you need to change your environment
right
and that's on a an individual level how
about a social level how do you have a
healthy population
well we know you try to create a more
equal society a fairer society you try
to make sure people have good housing
health care that sort of thing
so the biggest tragedy in my
view is this we as a society and this
happened in societies around the world
we're told a false story now it was
pitched to us as a story of
science and we organized our thinking
our sense of self or expectations of our
children
around that false around that story
and yet when you dig into that story you
find it's best understood as a
marketing story a commercially story
commercial story it's serving
financial interests the sort of
power interests the prestige of a
medical specialty
but it's doing extraordinary harm to
society it's it's
we have more people becoming disabled
you have so many people feel that they
they never live their full lives because
their emotions were muted
and the biggest thing for me is this
sense of philosophy
because it robs us of our sense that we
can be resilient human beings
and also look at shakespeare
look at your bible humans you know we're
very emotional creatures and and i just
think it gives us a false
philosophy as well and that's a huge
tragedy in my opinion
yeah that's really interesting i mean
for me
it's part of the sort of the crisis of
reductive scientific materialism
like yeah we're constantly kind of
reducing everything down to
and if you would and and also the the
realization that we're so much more
common
it's sort of a reductionistic idea of
the psyche as well
by reducing the psyche to kind of like
measurable
bits and pieces we're just we've we're
kind of
eviscerating the idea of being human and
this is one of the one of the
consequences of that kind of world view
i'd love to go into that into that more
but i um
maybe maybe towards the end because a
couple of things i'd like to to just
move the conversation on to
the question of the media and the
incentive structures
and why is this story not being told i
remember reading your book and
looking at other books and this topic as
well and just feeling incredibly
um angry at the level of
like the level of harm that is caused by
this and
just the level of silence that seems to
be
um on the part of of
of the media and on the part of kind of
the the the institutions
how is that maintained how is that kind
of this this story maintained
it's a really good question and
uh it seems hard to imagine that it
could have been maintained as well as it
has
there's a couple things the media
doesn't really know the science right
because you really have to dig into this
you have to understand how
science us how drugs are tested how you
can uh
bias trials by design you know there's a
lot of different ways
you also have to read the whole studies
you don't just read the abstract so
the first problem is even science
reporters
generally don't know
this literature not really okay what
they know
is what the people they interview tell
them
you know which are academic
psychiatrists and all right
um so why don't we know this story
one is because american psychiatry
basically
closed ranks in the night early 1980s
and said this is the story we're going
to tell
and they even had training workshops
where they taught
psychiatrists to tell this story and the
idea was
psychiatry in the 70s was sort of a
discipline and disrepute or
fearing for its survival and if they put
on the white coat
both literally and metaphorically or
figuratively
they could now present themselves to
it's sort of the image of infectious
disease doctors
remember how celebrated infectious
disease doctors are because we
we know we've minimized with infectious
disease with the arrival of the
antibiotics you know
anyway they decided and you can
you can really see this psychiatry
decided to tell a story in 1980 these
are brain illnesses therefore we're real
doctors
our drugs are good and really we if
these are illnesses it doesn't really
help to say that
talk therapy is good right they're
medical illnesses and what do you do
with medical illnesses you
you have a drug and who can prescribe
drugs that's psychiatrists
so that's the first thing the second
thing is
who really loved this story
pharmaceutical companies because now
you're going to take all these
ills that human beings that you can't
get it you can't
pass a drug for unhappiness okay you can
pass a drug for a medical condition
called anxiety or depression
so they're going to take all these ills
that human beings suffer all the time
it's you know beyond the asylum and now
they're going to make them diseases and
that's going to open up the market
so what happened you see that the
pharmaceutical companies start paying
academic psychiatrists to be their
advisors consultants
you know that sort of thing uh speakers
now and i'm talking about a lot of money
so what did the pharmaceutical thing
companies think they were doing when
they were hiring these academic
psychiatrists
they thought they were building markets
in other words
what did the academic psychiatrist start
thinking i'm so
brilliant i'm a world expert that i
deserve five hundred thousand dollars
for going on a speaking tour doing this
research or consulting
and you know the old thing it's hard to
convince a man of anything
or a person of anything if it goes
against their financial well-being
the actual sentiment is much more
concise than that
um once the profession
said to themselves this is the story
we're going to tell they're going to
start believing that story
and their and and and they're going to
start seeing whatever bits of science
that can support that story that's what
they're going to go on
to and they're going to find a way to
either ignore
or discount or even keep out of their
journals some of the
stuff that challenged that and what you
see quite clearly in american
psychiatric history those psychiatrists
who broke with that
and wanted to publish other types of
research they got killed
by killed i mean their their careers
went down the tubes so that became a
clear message that we
are going from psychiatry supported by
uh pharmaceutical money
we're gonna tell this story and okay so
we're committed to this story
and we're gonna believe it after a while
that's a that's the first part of this
meeting the second part is
they came up with a great strategy in
the basic in the late 80s early 90s to
discredit the critics
because unfortunately one very visible
critic was scientology
you know they started cchr and
scientology is clearly a cult right so
what happened was whenever critics came
forward
and you can even see this in documents
there's a there's a planning how do we
like
so in the early 1990s there was a worry
that antidepressants increase the risk
of suicide okay
and and eli lilly held a meeting what
are we going to say and he said
ah say this is coming from the
scientologist
because once that is then presented to
the media
i'm a science reporter i got
scientologists supposedly
over here criticizing the drugs and i
have people at
johns hopkins harvard stanford telling
me a different story
now who am i going to believe
not only like who am i going gonna
believe i don't want anything to do
being tainted with that scientology
brush
and they would throw it at anybody
basically that you know
stood up and criticized so it was a
brilliant public relations thing
say that people you know and they would
say all these people criticizing that
they're flat earthers
so they they managed as part of the
narrative
that became the organizing narrative as
critics of psychiatry critics of these
drugs
are flat earthers they're non-scientific
people they're members of a cult
now once that was in place now it's it's
it's diminishing but that was in place
in the 1990s and early 2000s when this
narrative really took hold
now i'm an editor and i say david
go out and do a story i don't want to
come back and hear that like
uh these drugs don't you know maybe
they're increasing suicide or
you know they don't work over the long
term and then i'm going to say
you're the reporter i'm going to go like
this is going to get people stop taking
the drugs if you report something like
that
we're going to be doing harm and and it
just became like and then finally
how many editors haven't yet reporters
ended up taking the drugs themselves
because once you move into that for a
while you're going to be a believer
right
anyway long story short is that there
were a lot of storytelling influences
that made it difficult for critics
and there was a lot of money and power
and prestige behind the
conventional narrative yeah it's
i find it really interesting we there's
another person we've had on the channel
quite a bit called eric weinstein
who talks about the he he
he's called some he's come up with the
term the disc
the distributed information suppression
complex
and i think yeah i think it fits
perfectly with this
he basically describes how in many
different areas of
many different institutions they
coalesce around certain narratives for
prestige and financial and other kind of
incentive structures
and then anyone who deviates from that
is like taken out
he calls it the platter of plomo so
you're either bought off or you're
dispatched that it comes from the i
think
what's his name escobar used to kind of
keep people in line in medellin and
colombia by
either bribery or or assassination and
he
he talks about this in i think this is
one of the the most
obvious examples of how that system
works that i've
that i've seen yeah i i that's uh
exactly what happened that's a brilliant
way to summarize it
yeah and you know what's brilliant about
this is you can see the incentives i
mean
and you can see who benefits from this
so you can see
why you would have this sort of uh you
know thing in operation
that's a brilliant i love that sort of
acronym too that's a great acronym
and what what drives you in this in this
work
what why why are you sort of plowing
this furrow and have you felt
it a bit of a lonely battle over the
years
um there are elements of loneliness
that's for sure there are also uh
elements of great reward
and the reward comes from um
this counter narrative let's call it a
counter narrative that i've been talking
about
but it's it's getting more and more
accepted
it's growing okay and it's making
inroads even into
you know journals and that sort of thing
psychiatric journals
so there is some reward uh
for pursuing a counter narrative
that even as time goes by gets stronger
not weaker
like new evidence just continues to come
along
that supports your the counter narrative
and and revealing the falseness of the
you know of the convention there so
there's something rewarding about that
i've had so many many many many people
write me and say ah now i understand my
life
i got i got screwed up on these drugs
uh and and many now so often it's hard
to get off these drugs okay but i know
many people have and they feel like they
got their lives back
and of course it's rewarding to be part
of the
an underdog battle right david versus
goliath
that's always fun that said
it's tough because you get
excommunicated people think you're a
little nutty or something
how could you how could you be the how
could you be the one that understands
things better
you know how can your narrative be
better than
uh the narrative put together by the
american psychiatric association
and i say well it's not my name it's
actually their name
it's their science it's not my science
what's wearing though okay so i know by
the way
david you meet so many great people
engaged human people humanistic people
you also have the joy of you know in
journalism the old adage of like
afflict the comfortable and comfort the
afflicted
and here you feel so often you're
comforting the afflicted
and afflicting the comfort and that's
pretty great
i mean it fits with sort of meaningful
journalism
and you know when we we talked about the
whole philosophy i just think it's so
important it's such a
big story of how it's changed our
society how we raise our kids and all
that so all that makes it meaningful
the hard part is you feel like you're
making a little bit of progress
things are getting into this like uh
journals but
nothing is really changing
people still getting diagnosed left and
right people still putting
on drugs left and right kids still being
put on the drugs left and right
and so the the weariness is am i just
banging my head on those swamps
and i sort of been at this now like 20
years
and i'm more convinced than ever
that the conventional narrative is a
false narrative as
as shown in their own literature um
if you go back to madden america there's
sort of predictions
that uh in both of those books
okay there's the conventional narrative
here's the counter narrative we're going
to see which ones
what is the data that is generated in
the next year is going gonna show us
okay
and in both cases it was the
counter narrative that actually played
out in as new data
came in now you might say wow that's
pretty
you know wow that was good predictive
powers
it wasn't it's what the science that had
been done to that
time was predicting you know what i mean
there was 40 years of
of research sort of saying this is
what's going to happen and it was just
taking that
and and sort of you know why should
things change if
you're just you're still doing the same
sort of thing you're perturbing
neurotransmitter systems
anyway it's an important battle i think
it's a battle so meaningful to people's
lives
dave and goliath battles are good but
it's where it's into
and and you wish
it's also a little heartbreaking you
know what i mean like i i
when i heard the story from this guy who
just i lost my life
and i just broke up with a girl it's
you know those and then i'll get you
know i'll get emails from parents who've
lost their kids and
it's hard a lot of suffering
and i'd just love to to close by
returning to the piece you mentioned
about
the philosophy because i think that's
such an important piece
of the sort of the reductionistic idea
and it reminds me a little bit of
michael pollan's
work i don't know if you're familiar
with his yeah so he did
he did a book called how to change your
mind about psychedelic therapies
but before that he actually i was a huge
fan of his stuff
for his food work and i think it was in
defense of food he talked about
the ideology of nutritionism
like the the kind of the idea that we
can break all the foods down and we can
understand them just through kind of
vitamins and that
they would they were just effectively
kind of vitamin and carb and
fat delivery systems and he said that's
that's the problem a lot of our diet
with a lot of our understanding of diet
because we're not we're not seeing
things holistically
and he said it was a wonderful line he
said who knows what transpires in the
soul of a carrot
and there's a kind of sort of natural
mysticism of the or a mysticism of the
natural world in his work of
of like we if we if we start to break
things apart
and try to fix them um in
in very reductionistic terms we're
missing the essence of of
of this the living system and it's a
real problem and i see that so much in
this
uh in in psychiatry and in in this kind
of
the medical model of the psyche
in particular i'd love to hear you just
talk a little bit more about the
philosophy aspect of it
yeah um it
it it it starts from a sort of
mechanistic view of human beings right
and and of course medicine did advance
in many ways from a
mechanistic point of view you know you
understood the heart and these sort of
things
at the same time i think medicine as a
whole has faltered for that
because they're not seeing that these
holistic you know these
we're not just a heart we're not just
this system we're not just that system
that all these things are interrelated i
mean
talking physically now right i'm not
even getting in so much
into the brain um but now add in the
brain
and now adding consciousness now and
this
unbelievable ability to feel and know
the world
and know a little bit about your mind at
least the conscious part
i think if you go through human history
right
that we can and and people are
societies are trying to understand
themselves and they tell stories about
like how we got here and
what is our relationship to nature and
what is the mind
and god and all there's a mystery to it
there's a profundity to it
and there's a recognition of
there's a recognition of sort of what
you're saying
here is that each of us is a mystery
we need to be humble as we try to
understand each other
understand ourselves understand our
place in nature
and i think that philosophy by the way
helps breed uh a sense of responsibility
to yourself but also a sense of
um empathy towards other human beings
also a sense of societies need each
other
so in other words um out of this
humility
uh out of this holistic vision of things
um we're not just islands you know we're
not
we're more like a bee culture so to
speak if you understand what i mean here
in other words
we don't exist alone we exist in
ecological niches and societies that
sort of thing
so that's what and that's a sort of view
of life you get by
reading history reading the bible
reading religious tracts reading
reading novels that's what you see right
and now it's almost like with this
mechanistic this reductionist point of
view we lose all that we lose that
knowledge that lore that sense of self
that sense of society and it's like
oh the problem it's in you david you're
depressed
uh something wrong with your head it's
so it's like the most impoverished
philosophy imaginable
and it and it's an impoverished
philosophy that
becomes a hindrance to creating a more
just society
of being a more loving society of being
a more forgiving society
embracing diversity right embracing
people who are different
so i i think if if
we go back to this sense of philosophy
and what's loss
the biggest loss is
it's an impoverishment of what it means
to be alive
it's an impoverished philosophy and
if a person has that sense of self it's
just such um
i don't know i mean it's it's it's just
it's like you lose yourself
if that makes sense because you're just
saying ah
this you know all my problems are in my
head
uh it's some sort of chemistry i i just
i can't imagine if i were going to raise
a kid i can't
think of any philosophy i would want
them not to have
and any sort of history the training
learning
that's exactly what i would not want
them to think about society themselves
others and that sort of thing so if
if we could have a society where we
could just get rid of this narrative
and sort of revisit literature
history would be a healthier society
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media
it was built for these times of crisis
and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times
more films and also for our rebel wisdom
members
weekly sense making calls with our
amazing interviewees
and also we're introducing the wisdom
gym
a place to practice some of the skills
that we've talked about on the channel
thanks for watching